Guide to the Fowler Family Papers, 1779-1870 RL.10111
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Fowler family papers
1779-1870
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Fowler family
RL.10111
4.2 Linear Feet 9 Boxes; 1 volume
Included in this collection are records, 1779-1809, of a mercantile business run by Stephen Fowler, Fairfield, Connecticut, and after 1805 of Trenton, Jones Co., North Carolina, which engaged in trade between New York and North Carolina. Stephen's son Joseph about 1820 engaged in the export of lumber, naval stores, tobacco, grain, and blackeyed peas from North Carolina to Bermuda; and later in coastal trade from New Bern to New York. There is also correspondence relating to his duties as U.S. deputy marshal, Pamlico District, N.C., 1831-1860. Family correspondence predominates between 1840 and 1860. For the Civil War years there are many letters from Joseph S. Fowler, Jr., written largely from the Confederate Commissary Office, Kinston, N.C. The collection also includes two Yale university diplomas; a ledger of Joseph S. Fowler, (1817-1834), 1836, 1866, 1 vol.; financial and legal papers, 1800-1860; the logbook of Absalom Fulford kept on the Neuse River lightship, 1845-1849, recording weather and the passage of ships; and business letters to DeWitt C. Fowler and Brother, Bay River (N.C.) general store and liquor merchants.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Biographical Note
Stephen Fowler (d. 1829) ran a mercantile business, first in Fairfield, Connecticut, and after 1805 in Trenton, Jones County, North Carolina., which engaged in trade between New York and North Carolina. Stephen's son, Joseph, in about 1820 expanded the business to engage in the export of lumber, naval stores, tobacco, grain, and blackeyed peas from North Carolina to Bermuda; and later in coastal trade from New Bern to New York. He also worked as as U.S. deputy marshal, Pamlico District, North Carolina from 1831-1860. His brother Dewitt C. Fowler, was a general store and liquor merchant in Bay River, North Carolina. His son, Joseph S. Fowler, Jr. (1838-1873), served in the Civil War, largely at the Confederate Commissary Office in Kinston, North Carolina.
Collection Overview
The Fowler family papers collection Includes records, 1779-1809, of a mercantile business run by Stephen Fowler, Fairfield, Connecticut, and after 1805 of Trenton, Jones County, North Carolina, which engaged in trade between New York and North Carolina. Stephen's son Joseph, about 1820, engaged in export of lumber, naval stores, tobacco, grain, and blackeyed peas from North Carolina to Bermuda; and later in coastal trade from New Bern to New York. There is also correspondence relating to his duties as U.S. deputy marshal, Pamlico District, North Carolina, 1831-1860. Family correspondence predominates between 1840 and 1860. For the Civil War years there are many letters from Joseph S. Fowler, Jr., written largely from the Confederate Commissary Office, Kinston, North Carolina.
The collection also includes diplomas; a ledger of Joseph S. Fowler, (1817-1834), 1836, 1866, 1 vol.; financial and legal papers, 1800-1860; broadsides concerning state policies; the logbook of Absalom Fulford kept on the Neuse River lightship, 1845-1849, recording weather and the passage of ships; certificates for jurors, U.S. District Court, New Bern, 1839-1858; business letters addressed to DeWitt C. Fowler and Brother at Bay River, 1860-1868, a general store and liquor dealer; and a few items relating to North Carolina schools. Among correspondents in the collection are Silvester Brown, Benjamin Q. Tucker, Absalom Fulford, and Wesley Jones.
Provenance
The Fowler family papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library between 1951-1958.
Coastwise shipping -- Middle Atlantic States; Alcohol -- Marketing -- North Carolina; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Merchants -- Connecticut -- Fairfield; Logbooks; Lightships -- North Carolina; Bermuda Islands -- Commerce -- North Carolina; North Carolina -- Commerce -- Bermuda Islands; Naval stores; United States marshals; Merchants -- North Carolina; Fowler family; Confederate States of America. Army -- Commissariat; Fowler, DeWitt C.; Yale University -- Students; Fowler, Stephen; Fulford, Absalom; Fowler, Joseph S., Jr.; Fowler, Joseph S.
- Correspondence, 1795-1870 and undated
  - Correspondence, 1795-1839; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1840-1870 and undated; 1 folders (Box 2)
- Legal Papers, 1797-1868
  - Legal papers, 1797-1837; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Legal papers and jury certificates, 1838-1868; 5 folders (Box 3)
- Financial Papers, 1790-1869 and undated
  - Financial papers, 1790-1829; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Financial papers, 1830-1855; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Financial papers, 1856-1859; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Financial papers, 1860-1869 and undated; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Joseph S. Fowler ledger, 1817-1836, 1866 (Volume F:6877)
- Other Papers
  - Miscellaneous printed materials, undated; 3 items (Box 8)
  - Logbook of the Neuse River lightship, 1845-1849; 1 folders (Box 9)